#### Contact

redheadrn60@aol.com

www.linkedin.com/in/liz-fackinaaaa8024 (LinkedIn)

### Top Skills

Nursing
Critical Care
Healthcare

# Liz Fackina

Nurse Education Manager, Critical Care, Nurse Leader, Nursing School Professor at Mount Sinai Health System New York, New York

## Summary

Healthcare industry leader and professional registered nurse with more than 25 years of progressive experience including hospital administration, patient care, nursing education, nursing leadership, value analysis, and project management. Contributed to institutional outcomes through innovative process improvement, implementation of evidence based practice, new technology and quality improvement initiatives. Core competencies include:

- Leadership and mentoring
- Education & Training
- Engaging and Collaboration with All Levels of the Multidisciplinary Team
- Product/Technology Evaluation & Selection
- Presentations and Teaching, EVP
- JCAHO Regulatory Compliance & Quality
- Process & Performance Improvement
- Policy & Procedure Development
- Team building and Staff Development
- Change Agent and Transformational Leader

Accomplishments include the development and successful implementation of a CRRT program that brought CRRT back to a facility after nine years. The development of a bypass PACU to ICU Educational program that improved patient flow through and delivery of care. Several system-wide evidence based on-line educational programs: Pressure Ulcer Prevention, Lateral Violence in Nursing, Hemodynamics, Organ Donation and Sepsis. Co-developed and led a Joint Commission Preparation Course for registered nurses. As a critical care nurse leader, divisional projects include: Critical Care Nursing Grand Rounds (nurses presenting to nurses), an ABCDE Protocol, critical care orientation, a CCRN review course and policy development as co-chair of the Critical Care Interdisciplinary Practice Council. As lead educator for the LVAD program, I was instrumental in obtaining NYU's first disease specific

certification. Served as nurse expert on Value Analysis Committees for six years and served as Director and Chair of the NYU Value Analysis Committee; evaluates, selects, coordinates and plans pilots, trials, education and implementation of products, processes and technologies that impact delivery of care and outcomes. Seasoned Nurse educator, change agent and health care leader with a track record of impact positive change, outcomes and improvements on the unit, divisional and enterprise level.

## Experience

Mount Sinai Health System

Nurse Education Manager, Critical Care, Nurse Leader, Nursing School Professor

December 2019 - Present (8 months)

Greater New York City Area

#### **RWJBarnabas** Health

Nurse Educator Cath Lab/Critical Care, Step Down Unit & Interventional Radiology
March 2017 - Present (3 years 5 months)

New Jersey

Orient nurses, nurse externs, and patient care technicians in general, critical care and step down nursing units. Educate, evaluate, and support nurses and clinical staff on the units daily. Conduct and design targeted and house wide educational programs for nursing staff. Plan curriculum and teach the critical care course and courses and topics related to critical care and step down units. Participate in code blue and rapid response team incidents, and provide education and support courses include PCT Orientation, Preceptor Course, EKG Course, Back to Basics, Critical Care, and General Nursing Skills Labs, IV Therapy, Developed a Step Down Unit Course and Back to Basics Course. Co-developed and implemented a unit specific turning and pressure ulcer prevention program that has reduced unit acquired HAPI to Active Member and participant of Quality and Safety, Professional Practice and Nursing Research & Evidenced Based Practice Nurse Practice Councils. Served as a Magnet Champion during the most recent, highly successful magnet survey and Cerner super user during the implementation of new EMR System

NYC Health + Hospitals

Director Staff Development & Professional Practice and Wound Care, Credentialed Trainer Epic ClinDoc June 2018 - December 2019 (1 year 7 months) Bronx

NYU Langone Medical Center
Director Value Analysis, NYU Langone Hospitals
July 2013 - March 2017 (3 years 9 months)
Greater New York City Area

Facilitates the value analysis processes to support institutional goals, objectives, high standards of care, cost control and product standardization. Assesses cost and benefit of new products, processes and technology in relation to impact on patient care, patient safety, caregiver safety, physician satisfaction, and institutional outcomes. Partners with clinicians, hospital leadership, and supply chain team members to coordinate the pilot and evaluation process. Clinical liaison between Supply Chain and the NYU multidisciplinary team.. Communicate with NYU team members to track progress and success of new products, practices and technology implemented. Facilitates the Medical Surgical Value Analysis process. Active member of various NYU Nursing Leadership Committees and Nurse Practice Councils.

### NYU Langone Health

Critical Care Nurse Educator - World Class Academic Medical Center January 2011 - June 2013 (2 years 6 months)

Orient nurses, nurse externs, and patient care technicians in general and critical care nursing units. Educate, evaluate and support nurses and clinical staff on the units daily. Conduct and design targeted and house wide educational programs for nursing staff. Plan curriculum and teach the critical care course and courses and topics related to critical care. Teach and participate in code blue and rapid response team training. Co-chair of the critical care interdisciplinary practice council. Represent the Department of Nursing Education and work directly with the Value Analysis Chairperson and committee to analyze new products and services for NYULMC. Coordinate product trials, implementation of new technology and equipment and education. Mentor nurses in NYU Nurse Residency Program for research projects. Lead educator for Left Ventricular Assistive Device Program (HM II, Centrimag, Impella), instrumental in achieving NYU's first disease specific certification. Designed and implemented education plans for Weaning and Delirium/ABCDE Protocols in the Intensive Care Units. Designed and implemented on line learning modules for house wide education (Sepsis MRT

and LVAD). Member of Bully Task Force, a formal research and planning committee that promotes and supports a healthy work environment. Plan and teach critical care specific courses CRRT, Intra Aortic Balloon Pump, Aquapheresis, EKG Course and the critical care nursing orientation course.

Saint Joseph Health System

Critical Care Nurse Educator - Magnet Facility and Beacon Critical Care Units

March 2009 - June 2011 (2 years 4 months)

Paterson, New Jersey

Orient nurses to Critical Care. Identify strengths, learning needs and provide education and resources for nurses to successfully complete orientation through ICU, CCU, IRC, and OHR. Meet with nurses and preceptors to track progress and support the orientation process. Participate in hospital wide education initiatives and programs. Plan and coordinate the Critical Care Course, CCRN Review Course, Preceptor Course, Open Heart Course. Prepare presentations and lecture for portions of the course. Provide unit specific education as needed. Attend and complete projects for committees (New Products Committee, Research Committee, Palliative Care Committee, DVT Committee, Critical Care Committee).

#### Saint Barnabas Health Care System

Critical Care Nurse Educator - Largest Healthcare System in NJ August 2007 - March 2009 (1 year 8 months)

Orient nurses hired by the Medical Center to Critical Care. Identify strengths, learning needs and provide education and resources for nurses to successfully complete orientation through ICU, CCU, NSICU and PACU. Meet with nurses and preceptors daily to track progress and support the orientation process. Participate in hospital wide education initiatives (quarterly educational updates, annual competencies and educational roll-outs of new initiatives and practices). Participate in skill lab training, and provide monthly lectures for Conscious Sedation, IV Therapy, Phlebotomy and Basic Life Support. Plan and coordinate the Critical Care Course, a system-wide course held twice a year for nurses new to critical care. Prepare presentations and lecture for portions of the course. Provide unit specific in-services as needed and as requested by managers.

Saint Michael's Medical Center Registered Nurse - Cardiac Cath Lab Staff Nurse April 2005 - August 2007 (2 years 5 months) Cardiac Catheterization Lab April 2005 to August 2007
Assist with diagnostic and interventional cardiac, carotid, peripheral, renal, mesenteric procedures. Assist with electrophysiology, IVUUS, rotoblader and angiojet procedures. Rotate as charge nurse. Weekend and evening call for acute myocardial infarctions.

Cardiac Recovery Room Registered Nurse - Open Heart Recovery Staff Nurse February 2001 - April 2005 (4 years 3 months)

Receive and care for post cardiac surgical patients. Continuous one to one monitoring of oxygenation, hemodynamics, neurological status, vital signs, cardiac output, intake and output, titrate drips, manage and document intra-aortic balloon pump, CVVH, peritoneal dialysis, administration of blood products and medications. Provide support and teaching to patients and family. Remove arterial lines, pulmonary artery catheters, triple lumen catheters and extubate patients as ordered. Implement ACLS protocols when necessary in unit as a code team member. Rotate as charge nurse.

University of Medicine and Dentistry
Registered Nurse \_ Open Heart & ICU Overflow Staff Nurse
November 1999 - February 2001 (1 year 4 months)

Care for post cardiac surgical and cardiac catheterization patients as well as a variety of other intensive care unit patients. (Cardiac Surgery Care as stated above).

Saint Barnabas Health Care Registered Nurse - Intensive Care Staff Nurse September 1997 - November 1999 (2 years 3 months)

Provide all aspects of care for one to three critically ill patients. Experience in post neurological surgery patients; management of ICP and CSF/ ventriculostomy drainage. Rotating charge responsibilities for thirteen bed unit. Member of hospital code team. Nurse preceptor. Serve as ICU/CCU resource person on various management and joint commission performance improvement teams.

Union Hospital Registered Nurse - Telemetry Staff Nurse March 1996 - August 1997 (1 year 6 months)

Provided care for six to eight patients. Rotated charge responsibilities for fortyfour bed unit. Nurse Preceptor. Saint Barnabas Medical Center Registered Nurse - Medical Surgical Staff Nurse March 1995 - August 1997 (2 years 6 months)

Worked nights on the GYN-Oncology/Major Abdominal Surgery Unit. Provided all aspects of nursing care for ten to twelve patients per shift. Charge Nurse responsibilities included management of unit, patient care assignment, overseeing the LPNs and care for thirty two patients.

Nurse Extern, 2700 (GYN-Oncology

Saint Barnabas Medical Center Administrative Assistant to AVP March 1990 - May 1994 (4 years 3 months)

Responsibilities included researching patient complaints and preparing response letters to patients and appropriate staff members. Developed report of emergency room patient survey results for management indicating areas that need improvement. Developed a sick/overtime/agency analysis report used hospital-wide that dramatically reduced personnel expenses. Scheduled and assisted in planning quality improvement, community relations and other work related projects. Various administrative duties and tasks as required

Waterfront Investme
Property Management, Sales & Rental Agent
March 1986 - March 1990 (4 years 1 month)
Hoboken, New Jersey

Rental property manager of 160 Units in Newark, Jersey City and Hoboken. Sales, rentals, customer service and represented the property owners in land lord tenant disputes and settlements. Planned company events, board of advisory sessions and staff customer service and industry update educational sessions.

### Education

Thomas Edison State University

MSN, Clinical Education Specialist · (2008 - 2011)

Thomas Edison State University BSN, Nursing · (2004 - 2007)

Elizabeth General Medical Center/UCC School of Nursing - ASN

ASN, Nursing · (1992 - 1995)